<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="oil_properties">
        <item>Sweet Almond oil is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nIt contributes to: stable medium lather, conditioning, moisturizing, mild cleansing.
            \n\nOften used for superfatting soaps. Sweet almond oil is often used as an emollient in skin creams and balms.</item>
        <item>Aloe vera butter is an extract of aloe vera, aloe barbadensis, in a coconut fatty fraction.
            \n\nAloe vera butter aids in rapid hydration of dry skin caused by eczema, psoriasis, rosacea, sun burn, wind burn,
            and general chapping.</item>
        <item>Apricot Kernel is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nIt is a smooth and lightweight oil, high in Vitamin A and minerals, often used for superfatting.
            \n\nIt Contributes to stable medium lather, mild cleansing.
            \n\nAlso popular as a massage oil, known for its ability to penetrate the skin without leaving an oily feel,
            it has a superb texture that is great for all skin types.</item>
        <item>Avocado oil is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe, often used for superfatting soaps.
            It contributes to Medium lather, mild cleansing.
            \n\nAvocado oil contains vitamins A, D, E and other minerals which makes it a great addition to facial bars or bars for elder skin.
            \n\nAlso used in massage oils, creams, lotions and hair products.</item>
        <item>Babassu oil is a great oil to use in place of coconut oil for those that have a coconut allergy.
            \n\nContributes to: soap hardness, fluffy lather, quicker trace, high cleansing but a bit milder than coconut oil.
            \n\n
            Beneficial for both dry and oily complexions, gently moisturizing the skin without contributing to an oily sheen.
            Especially suitable for eczema, itchy, dry and inflamed skin.</item>
        <item>Beeswax can help make a somewhat harder bar of soap. Used at 1~3\%% of total oils,
            acts as an emulsifier while stirring to trace and may help prevent soap ash while curing. Inhibits lather at higher amounts.
            \n\nNatural, unrefined beeswax has the smell of honey which persists through saponification better than
            if honey itself is used. Beeswax contains a high percentage of unsaponifiables.
            \n\nBeeswax has emollient, soothing and softening properties and helps the skin retain moisture.</item>
        <item>Contributes to: stable lather, conditioning. Goes rancid very quickly.
            \n\nBorage oil is degraded by heat, light, humidity, and exposure to oxygen. It should be stored in a cool, dark place.
            \n\nBorage oil is one of the richest sources of gamma linolenic acid plus
            it contains important vitamins and minerals. It is often used in high end cosmetic formulations to nourish and
            hydrate the skin. Said to be beneficial for maturing skin and for damaged skin where regeneration of new skin cells
            is needed.</item>
        <item>Camellia oil can be used to make soaps that are extra gentle for those with sensitive skin.
            \n\nIt Contains antioxidants that help to revitalize and rejuvenate the hair, nails and skin.
            \n\nThis oil will provide a small amount of hardness for your soap.</item>
        <item>Contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, slower trace, softer soap.
            \n\nUse canola oil to partially replace more expensive oils like olive.</item>
        <item>15~20\%% castor oil is used in shampoo bars or shaving bars.
            \n\nContributes to: fluffy lather, stable lather, conditioning, moisturizing, quicker trace, softer soap. Often used to superfat soaps.
            \n\nCastor oil is unique in being almost entirely composed of ricinoleic fatty acid, found in no other oils and
            possessing a high affinity for water molecules. This makes it an excellent humectant, attracting and holding moisture
            to the skin.
            \n\nCastor oil should be used at low percentages to avoid overly soft soaps.</item>
        <item>Cocoa butter contributes to: soap hardness, mild stabilizing lotion like lather, conditioning, moisturizing, quicker trace.
            \n\nWhen used as a superfatting oil it acts to lay down a protective layer which holds moisture to the skin.
            It is an excellent moisturizer that melts at body temperature, leaving the skin feeling soft and silky smooth.
            \n\nIt has a natural chocolate scent but it is also available in an unscented version.
            \n\nCocoa butter contains natural antioxidants that help to prevent rancidity. </item>
        <item>Contributes to: soap hardness, fluffy lather, large fluffy bubbles, quicker trace, high cleansing.
            \n\nCoconut oil makes soaps lather beautifully
            but can be drying when it makes up an overly large portion of your soap fats,
            however you can always use a higher superfatting to counteract the drying effect.
            It will make a very hard, white bar of soap that lathers well even in very hard water or sea water.
            \n\nCoconut oil is light and not greasy and is resistant to spoiling. Used in skin care formulations,
            coconut oil is emollient, moisturizing, conditioning and protecting to the skin.
            This oil is solid at room temperatures under 76 degrees and liquid at higher temperatures.</item>
        <item>Fractionated coconut oil is virgin coconut oil that has been distilled, allowing long-chain fatty acids to separate and solidify for removal.
            What remains is an ultralight, odorless coconut oil that stays liquid in form at cooler temps.
            \n\nThis oil is more easily absorbed by the skin, and less likely to clog pores than virgin coconut oil.
            It also maintains a longer shelf life, nourishing medium-chain fatty acids and essential nutrients in this form. </item>
        <item>Corn Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, soft soap.</item>
        <item>Cotton seed Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, silky feel.
            \n\nCottonseed oil produces thick and lasting lather, in addition to having emollient properties.
            \n\nIt can be vulnerable to rancidity, depending on storage temperature and humidity. </item>
        <item>Emu Oil is used as a superfatting oil in soapmaking.
            \n\nEmu Oil is reported to help heal skin tissues and help draw other ingredients down into the skin
            so they are more effective.</item>
        <item>Evening Primrose Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, emollience.
            \n\nEvening primrose oil is an exceptionally fine textured oil, Absorbed quickly into the skin,
            it is one of the most popular sources of an essential fatty acid called Gamma Linolenic Acid (GLA).
            \n\nEvening primrose oil is said to be effective in helping those with dry skin, eczema and psoriasis.</item>
        <item>Flax seed oil is said to soften and heal skin abrasions and scars, and to reduce swelling and
            redness of rashes and lesions from skin disease. Also used in creams, lotions and balms.</item>
        <item>Goat Fat has very little odder and makes a very hard bar.
            100\%% tallow soap with no superfatting makes great laundry soap, which is hard and white with mild stabilizing creamy lather.
            \n\nIt contributes to: soap hardness, stable lather, conditioning, quicker trace.</item>
        <item>Grapeseed is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe. Medium lather, mild cleansing.
            \n\nAlso used in soaps as a superfatting oil, grapeseed oil is a lightweight oil that absorbs into the skin quickly
            without leaving a heavy greasy feeling.
            \n\nIt has mildly astringent qualities and is said to be useful for acne and other skin complaints.</item>
        <item>Hazelnut is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nContributes to: stable medium lather, conditioning, moisturizing, softer soap, slower trace.
            \n\nHazelnut Oil has a soft, natural, nutty fragrance and contains vitamins, minerals, and protein.
            \n\nIt is an excellent carrier for essential oils, hazelnut oil is very easily absorbed, leaving no oily residue.</item>
        <item>Hemp Seed is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nContributes to: stable medium lather, conditioning, silky feel, softer soap, slower trace.
            \n\nHemp seed oil is not as stable as some other oils and can spoil quickly.
            It creates a silky bar of soap even if it is only used to superfat your batch.
            Since it is prone to spoilage, keep it as a small percentage  of your mix to avoid having a soft soap
            that may spoil in a few months. Store unused oil in the freezer or refrigerator.
            \n\nFresh hemp seed oil has a green color which becomes lighter with age.
            Hemp seed oil will warn you with a painty smell long before it is actually rancid.
            \n\nIt is rich with proteins, vitamins, minerals, and essential fatty acids and is excellent for all skin and hair needs.</item>
        <item>Horse oil is known for its healing properties and highly moisturizing capabilities.</item>
        <item>Jojoba oil, a liquid wax, can kill lather when used in high amounts.
            \n\nContributes to: stable lather, conditioning, moisturizing, quicker trace.
            Actually mostly a liquid wax, jojoba does not lather much of itself, but rather acts to make existing lather
            from other oils more stable and long lasting.
            \n\nJojoba is good at conditioning skin. Because of its expense, it is usually used to superfat soap batches or in shampoo bars.
            It is said to be an excellent emollient for skin conditions like psoriasis or acne
            and has a chemical composition very close to the skin own sebum.
            \n\nJojoba oil is easily absorbed by the skin and promotes silky smooth skin. Jojoba Oil is stable and long lasting.</item>
        <item>Kukui Nut Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, silky feel.
            \n\nKukui nut oil is quickly absorbed into the skin. Excellent for skin conditioning after sun exposure
            and is said to be beneficial for acne, eczema, and psoriasis.</item>
        <item>Lard contributes to: soap hardness, mild stable creamy lather, conditioning, quicker trace.
            \n\nIts advantages are that it is cheap, easily obtainable, and makes a nice lathery, white bar of soap.
            \n\nThis fat should be combined with vegetable oils such as coconut or palm.
            Without other oils it can tend to not work very well in cold water.</item>
        <item>Macadamia Nut Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, moisturizing, silky feel.
            \n\nMacadamia has a long shelf life. It is easily absorbed into the skin and acts as an emollient.
            It is said to protect skin cells from deterioration and thus lead to better skin condition.</item>
        <item>Mango butter is yellowish and has almost no scent. It is a great moisturizer and should be used to superfat soap.</item>
        <item>Mink oil has superior absorption and nurturing properties, it penetrates skin deeply and quickly without clogging pores.
            \n\nIt lubricates skin, trapping moisture from the lower cell layers. It rehydrates skin, with a light barrier,
            preventing evaporation of moisture throughout a day.
            \n\nWhen used in soap, the bars are silky smooth. It is best to only use it up to 1.5\%% of your total oils
            in your soap making recipes. You can use more but it will decrease the lather in your bar.
            You can use it up to a 5\%% ratio, but no more. Add Coconut oil and Palm oils for nice, bubbly, lather.
            Use it with Castor oil to counteract some of its effects.</item>
        <item>Neem Tree Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning.
            \n\nSaid to have the ability to treat a variety of skin disorders such as dandruff.</item>
        <item>Olive Oil contributes to: soap hardness, stable lather, slippery feel, conditioning, moisturizing.
            \n\nOlive Oil attracts external moisture to your skin, helping to keep skin soft and supple.
            The low cleansing properties of olive oil make it very mild and nourishing.
            Soap for sensitive skin, elder skin or baby skin should include high amounts of olive.
            \n\nCastile soap is made with 100\%% olive oil, it has Low slippery lather, almost no bubbles, low cleansing.
            It makes a very soft bar of soap initially upon unmolding but cures into a rock hard bar.
            Soaps high in olive oil need longer to cure and unmold.</item>
        <item>Palm kernel oil is a great sub for coconut oil. It can be used with coconut oil to add some hardness to the bar.
            \n\nIt contributes to: soap hardness, fluffy lather, quicker trace.
            \n\nPalm Kernel oil makes a soap that is very hard and lathers well.
            It is processed from the core nut of the fruit of the same tropical oil palm plants
            that palm oil is derived from, but its composition and properties are not similar to palm oil.
            It is instead very similar to coconut oil and can be substituted for some of the coconut oil in soap formulas
            to make a harder bar.
            \n\nThis oil is solid at room temperatures.</item>
        <item>Palm oil is great for those that do not want to use animal fats such as lard or tallow.
            \n\nIt contributes to: soap hardness, mild stable lather, conditioning, silky feel, quicker trace.
            \n\nPalm oil makes a hard bar that cleans well and is also mild.</item>
        <item>Palm olein is the liquid fraction obtained during fractionation of palm oil.
            \n\nIt contains higher amounts of oleic (39–45%) and linoleic acids (10–13%) compared to palm oil (Siew, 2002).</item>
        <item>Peanut Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, softer soap.
            \n\nPeanut oil is prone to spoilage. It has a good amount of vitamin E.</item>
        <item>Pumpkin seed oil is valued for its skin healing properties.
            \n\nRich in antioxidants and essential fatty acids as well as high levels of Vitamins A, C and E.</item>
        <item>Red palm oil, which is bright orange, gets it color from carotenes (like carrots and tomatoes).
            It is bleached, refined and deodorized to give us the creamy palm oil that most of us are familiar with.
            \n\nRed Palm oil helps to produce a nice hard bar with stable lather.
            \n\nUsing too much within your recipe can produce an overly drying product.
            Keep it at less then 50\%% of the oils used for hand bars and less then 30\%% for facial bars.</item>
        <item>Rice Bran oil is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nIt contributes to: stable medium lather, mild cleansing, gives soap a sheen making it look less dull.
            \n\nRice bran oil is moisturizing and is a good choice for inclusion in formulations intended for mature,
            delicate or sensitive skin.</item>
        <item>Rosehip Seed Oil is believed to be the best oil available for antiageing and skin rejuvenation
            making it a good choice for use in soap and skin care products.</item>
        <item>Safflower oil is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nIt contributes to: stable medium lather, conditioning, moisturizing, silky feel, softer soap.
            \n\nSafflower oil is an unsaturated oil, valuable for its moisturizing properties.
            Limited shelf life. It has an exceptionally high linoleic acid content and is an excellent moisturizing choice
            for in skin creams and lotions.</item>
        <item>Sesame Seed Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning, moisturizing, silky feel, softer soap.
            \n\nSesame oil makes a good superfatting oil. Has a strong nutty scent.
            Sesame oil has excellent longevity in massage preparations and is said to be good for psoriasis, eczema, rheumatism,
            and arthritis.</item>
        <item>Shea butter can produce hard, long lasting bar with mild stabilizing lotion like lather.
            \n\nIt contributes to: soap hardness, stable lather, conditioning, silky, slippery feel, quicker trace.
            Shea butter is a popular superfatting agent and contains a large percentage of ingredients
            that do not react with the lye, thus remaining in the soap to nourish your skin.
            \n\nShea butter is said to be beneficial for treating dry skin, blemishes, skin discoloration, scars and wrinkles.</item>
        <item>Vegetable shortening performs similarly as palm oil.</item>
        <item>Soybean oil is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nIt contributes to: stable medium lather, conditioning, slower trace, mild cleansing.</item>
        <item>Sunflower oil is a wonderful sub for some of the olive oil in a recipe.
            \n\nIt contributes to: stable medium lather, conditioning, silky feel, softer soap, slower trace.
            \n\nSunflower oil contains Vitamin E, so it naturally resists going rancid.</item>
        <item>100\%% tallow soap with no superfatting makes great laundry soap, which is hard and white with mild stabilizing creamy lather.
            \n\nIt contributes to: soap hardness, stable lather, conditioning, quicker trace.</item>
        <item>Walnut Oil is an emollient oil which is said to help regenerate, tone and moisturize damaged dry skin
            and to aid in preventing wrinkles, controlling eczema, dandruff and rough, dry or sunburned skin.</item>
        <item>Wheat Germ Oil contributes to: stable lather, conditioning.
            \n\nWheat germ oil is emollient, antioxidant and rich in natural vitamin E. Can be used to nourish dry
            or cracked skin and soothes skin problems such as eczema and psoriasis.
            \n\nWheat germ oil should be kept refrigerated.</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>